<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<job-description>
  <title>Medical Laboratory Scientist/Medical Laboratory Technician</title>
  <company>Mercyhealth</company>
  <location>
    <city>Harvard</city>
    <state>Illinois</state>
    <address>901 Grant St</address>
  </location>
  <employment-type>PART_TIME</employment-type>
  <section name="Overview">
    <list>
      <item>MLS/MLT</item>
      <item>Harvard Hospital and Medical Center, Harvard IL</item>
      <item>40 Hours/2 Weeks</item>
      <item>Day Shift</item>
    </list>
  </section>
  <section name="Responsibilities">
  </section>
  <section name="Education and Experience">
  </section>
  <section name="Certification/Licensure">
  </section>
  <section name="Special Physical Demands">
  </section>
  <section name="Culture of Excellence Behavior Expectations">
  </section>
  <section name="Benefits">
  </section>
  <section name="Responsibilities">
    <list>
      <item>Essential Duties and Responsibilities</item>
      <item>Utilize the Information System to receive patients, order and collect samples, result tests, answer questions from nurses and physicians, document quality control activities and produce reports required to perform job tasks.</item>
      <item>Confirms accuracy of patient sample identification prior to performing analyses; evaluates specimen quality and identifies when unacceptable. Documents information concerning quality of specimen, impact of sub-optimal specimens on test values. Initiates recollection procedure as indicated.</item>
      <item>Perform waived, moderate and high complexity lab tests as defined by CLIA in the lab specialties of hematology, urinalysis, chemistry and blood bank or microbiology by automated and manual methods according to defined policies and procedures.</item>
      <item>Analyze test results prior to release of information to chart for validity and accuracy. Recognizes subtle yet significant problems which occur with testing methodologies. Troubleshoots suspect test results using technical knowledge and experience. Implements corrective action when inaccurate, inappropriate findings/results/reports are identified.</item>
      <item>Performs high complexity tests such as bone marrow, sperm morphology, etc.</item>
      <item>Assure that designated turnaround times for results are met and that critical results are appropriately reported and documented.</item>
      <item>Perform quality control and proficiency testing procedures as defined by policy.</item>
      <item>Interpret and troubleshoot quality control results to ensure accurate and precise test results.</item>
      <item>Perform preventative maintenance, advanced troubleshooting and calibration of laboratory instrumentation.</item>
      <item>Participate in method and instrument evaluation and implementation.</item>
      <item>Investigates/resolves technical issues.</item>
      <item>Participates on interdepartmental committees or teams.</item>
      <item>Participates in teaching students and training new partners.</item>
      <item>Completes and signs off on competency checklists for techs.</item>
      <item>Develops updates and procedures as requested.</item>
      <item>Serves as a resource to inexperienced partners.</item>
      <item>Performs additional tasks such as scheduling, antibiograms, etc.</item>
      <item>Maintain competency in current procedures and gain competency for new methods implemented.&amp;nbsp;</item>
    </list>
  </section>
  <section name="Qualifications">
    <paragraph>1.Bachelor of Science degree in Medical Technology</paragraph>
    <paragraph>Must be qualified to perform high complexity testing according to CLIA 493.1489 Standard; Testing personnel qualifications.</paragraph>
    <paragraph>OR</paragraph>
    <paragraph>2.Associates degree in Medical Technology AND MLT certification</paragraph>
    <paragraph>Must be qualified to perform high complexity testing according to CLIA 493.1489 Standard; Testing personnel qualifications.</paragraph>
  </section>
</job-description>